Guide to the Ezio Levi Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ezio Levi papers
1863-1949
1910-1941
GEN MSS 1138
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.14
(8 boxes)
Levi, Ezio, 1884-1941
Lembo, Ferdinando
Scope and Contents
The Ezio Levi Papers consist of autograph manuscript and typescript writings and notes about Italian and Spanish literature and art, with related correspondence, printed articles, and photographs, 1910s-1940s and undated; biographical information about Levi and Flora Aghib Levi D'Ancona, undated; legal documents and correspondence relating to their immigration to the United States, 1930s-1940s; other correspondence, 1910s-1949, most relating to Levi's academic career in the United States; and lantern slides, possibly made by Ferdinando Lembo, of works of art in the Steri palace, Palermo, and relating to the legend of Tristan and Isolde, undated.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited in Yale University Library by Flora Aghib Levi D'Ancona, 1944; additional correspondence added, 1949. Date of acquistion and transfer unknown.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Ezio Levi (1884-1941)
Ezio Levi, Italian philologist and author; also used the name Ezio Levi D'Ancona; professor of Romance languages at the Università di Napoli and Wellesley College. Levi immigrated to the United States as a Jewish refugee during World War II, with his wife, author and illustrator Flora Aghib Levi D'Ancona, and their children.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Writings, 1863-1941. II. Other Papers, 1916-1949.
Art -- Italy; Art -- Spain; College teachers -- United States; Italian literature; Jewish refugees -- United States; Philologists -- United States; Spanish literature; Tristan (Legendary character) -- Art; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, Italian; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees; Lantern slides -- Italy -- 20th Century; College teachers -- United States -- 20th Century; Philologists -- United States -- 20th Century; Aghib Levi D'Ancona, Flora; Levi, Ezio, 1884-1941; Palazzo Chiaramonte (Palermo, Italy) -- Pictorial works; Wellesley College -- Faculty
- Writings, 1863-1941, undated; Series I; 1.68; (4 boxes)
  - "Cantare di Madonna Elena Imperatrice", 1863-1894, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Gattinara, Carlos Quinto's Great Chancellor", undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - "Poesia popolare italiana", undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Spanish Speeches", 1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Lo Steri", undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Unsorted articles (printed), 1917-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notes
    - "Antonio de lo Frasso", undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Artisti", 1931-1937, undated; 2 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - "Ascanio Colonna", undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Corpus inscriptionum hispanicorum", undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Dante & His American Friends in Florence", undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
    - "Duccio de Gano", 1916, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "Iconografia del medio evo", undated; 3 (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
    - "La leggenda di Tristano", undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Lirica latina del medio evo", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Madrid, sec. XVIII", undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
    - "Novellieri dei cinquecenti", undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "Paravicino", undated; 2 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
    - "Poesie dei memoriali", 1891-1927, undated; 3 (Box 3, Folder 28-30)
    - "Poesie indite di sec. XIII & XIV", 1913-1917, undated; 3 (Box 3, Folder 31-33)
    - "Poesie popolari de codice Laurenziano XLII, 38", undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "Razza", undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 35-36)
    - "Regulae singulares", undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 37-38)
    - "Siviglia e la novela picaresca", undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - "Siviglia, sec. XIII", undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - "Storia di Giuseppe", 1934-1940, undated; 2 (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
    - "Tommaso Sibori", undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Unidentified, undated; 4 (Box 4, Folder 44-47)
  - Writings of Others
    - Calkins, Mary Whiton. The Works of Ezio Levi D'Ancona: Bibliography Republished June, 1940 (printed) (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Authors, B-F, 1940-1941, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Authors, G, 1933, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Authors, G-L, 1919-1941, undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Authors, M-W, 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 52)
- Other Papers, 1916-1949, undated; Series II; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  - Biographical information (Ezio Levi), 1941, undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Biographical information (Flora Aghib Levi D'Ancona), undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence and legal documents about immigration, 1930-1943, undated; 2 (Box 5, Folder 55-56)
  - Other Correspondence
    - Dupont, Henry (Hunter College), 1940-1941, undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Hunter College, 1940 February-October (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Steiner, Arpad (Hunter College), 1940-1941, undated (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Texas Technological College, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - University of Wisconsin, 1941, undated (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Yale University Library (from Flora Aghib Levi D'Ancona), 1949, undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Unsorted, 1916-1943, undated; 2 (Box 5, Folder 63-64)
  - "Lo Steri", undated; 9; 8 lantern slides (Box 6, Folder 65-73)
  - "Lo Steri", undated; 9; 8 lantern slides (Box 7, Folder 74-82)
  - "Tristano", undated; 9; 8 lantern slides (Box 8, Folder 83-91)